# **Nil Mamano**

nmamano.com github.com/nmamano linkedin.com/in/nmamano

**Summary** Strong Computer Science fundamentals and problem-solving skills from doing research in algorithm design. Strong communication skills from collaborating with researchers and teaching. Quick learner looking forward to dive into the latest technologies.

#### Education

PhD + Masters in Computer Science University of California Irvine, GPA 3.83/4

Sep 2015 - Dec 2019

**B.E. in Computer Science** Polytechnic University of Catalonia, GPA 3.8/4 (99th percentile)

Sep 2011 - Jul 2015

### **Skills**

Languages: C++, C, Python, Java, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Bash. Tools: Git, Github, Linux, Oracle Grid Engine.

### **Experience**

#### University of California Irvine

PhD Student Researcher

Sep 2015 - Dec 2019

- Co-authored 9 peer-reviewed articles on algorithm design.
- Designed data structures for matching drivers and passengers on a road network dynamically. Leveraged the topology of road networks to optimize the data structures and scale them to statewide networks with 100k+ edges. [Java]
- Led a research project: came up with an original research problem, engaged 3 colleagues to work on it, and collaborated with them
  to solve it, write a paper, and get it published. We designed an optimal algorithm for the knight tour problem. [Javascript]
- Designed clustering algorithms for partitioning data into balanced clusters, and applied them to gerrymandering prevention: they
  can partition a geographic region into compact and equal-population districts. Built a desktop application with a GUI to visualize
  and benchmark the algorithms. [C++, OpenGL, Javascript]
- Improved the runtime of the multi-fragment algorithm for Euclidean TSP from  $O(n^2)$  to  $O(n \log n)$ .

Teaching Assistant Sep 2016 – Jun 2018

- 100+ sessions teaching algorithms to groups of 50+ students, with excellent student evaluations.
- Championed the use of online automated grading to provide immediate feedback to the students and reduce the grading load. Led
  a study with 100+ students to measure the effect of automated grading.

**Undergrad Researcher** Feb 2015 – Jul 2015

Created SANA, a biological network alignment software that uses simulated annealing to predict the function of proteins. Ran large-scale experiments in a computing cluster to fine-tune the algorithm and managed to outperform the leading algorithms in accuracy and runtime simultaneously. [C++, Bash, Oracle Grid Engine]

#### Polytechnic University of Catalonia

Research Intern Feb 2014 – Sep 2014

Contributed to RACSO, a free online judge (automated grading tool) for compiler and automata theory courses. Built an interpreter for a C-like language used by the students to write their solutions, following Test-driven development. [C++]

## Selected projects

Built an efficient in-memory key-value Cache that supports timeouts, using templates and C++17 features. It implements Redis' algorithm to remove expired entries and has an LRU eviction mechanism. [C++]

# Selected publications

- "Euclidean TSP, Motorcycle Graphs, and Other New Applications of Nearest-Neighbor Chains" N. Mamano, A. Efrat, D. Eppstein,
   D. Frishberg, M.T. Goodrich, S. Kobourov, P. Matias, V. Polishchuk, International Symposium on Algorithms and Computation 2019
- "Stable-Matching Voronoi Diagrams: Combinatorial Complexity and Algorithms" G. Barequet, D. Eppstein, M. T. Goodrich, and
   N. Mamano, International Colloquium on Automata, Languages and Programming 2018
- "Reactive Proximity Data Structures for Graphs" D. Eppstein, M.T. Goodrich, and N. Mamano, Latin American Theoretical Informatics Symposium 2018
- "SANA: Simulated Annealing far outperforms many other search algorithms for biological network alignment" N. Mamano and W. Hayes, Bioinformatics: Oxford Journals 2017